Hi, this is Dr.
Dan here and we're going to be
going through practice problems
involving solution stoichiometry
and acid base chemistry.
So we're going to go through some
of the different types of practice
problems that you might encounter when
you come across solution stoichiometry,
especially involving acids and bases.
There's some key words that you might see
for these kinds of problems, including
neutralization, titration, solution
making, stoichiometry, uh, or pH, pOH.
There are a lot of little buzzwords
that we are going to be seeing
when you are dealing with these.
So look out for them.
You might have to solve for pH, pOH,
so we're going to go through two
practice problems in this video.
Please feel free to like and subscribe
for more of these videos in the future.
And we let's go into our example.
All right.
So our first example is the
following neutralization problem.
So the way that this is worded is
typically it gives you volumes that
are being mixed together and it
might use that buzzword neutralize.
Okay.
Or, titration is what you're looking
for, or mixing solutions is another
way that this might be shown.
So what this says is what volume,
and it says in milliliters, of 0.
450 molar nitric acid is
required to neutralize 27.
2 milliliters of 0.
245 molar barium hydroxide.
So let's kind of highlight
all the key things here.
So we have a concentration.
And that's for nitric acid.
We also have, uh, has to neutralize 27.
2 milliliters.
of barium hydroxide.
So these are our key things.
Let's go through the steps.
The first thing that we always have to
do for any of these types of problems
is when we're given names, we have
to write out the chemical reaction.
We need to know how many moles are
there going to be in this problem.
So this is one of the things
we are always looking for.
So the first thing what we had was nitric
acid and that said it was neutralizing
or Reacting with barium hydroxide.
So it's an acid base Reaction right nitric
acid is an acid barium hydroxide is a base
So with this what kind of reaction is it?
So if you're not don't remember reactions
go to my types of chemical types of
chemical reactions video That will help
you with that part But the whole idea
here is that this is all about outside
and inside are combining together.
Being that this is a double
replacement reaction, we could
label everything C A B plus C D.
We're labeling cations and anions
with our letters to help us see that.
Now with this, right, the first
one, so outside is it's showing
that we'll have water, so it's
going to be H and OH combined.
Whenever you have a hydroxide
polyatomic, a little tip is write it as
HOH until we have it balanced because
polyatomics are easier to balance
when they're written in this format.
Now, what's the other one?
The other one is barium hydroxide,
so we have, sorry not barium
hydroxide, barium nitrate.
It's going to combine together as well.
So it's BA.
Now we always swap,
drop, and check charges.
So it's a two plus on
barium, one minus on nitrate.
Um, so when we are doing that,
we got to swap, drop everything.
Same with H and OH.
They're plus and minus one,
so they're already balanced.
So we balance that, we do our swap, drop.
Now the thing is we have to make
sure are all of our atoms balanced.
Now, the key is here with balancing
atoms is you want to try to check
by starting with the polyatomics.
So, what do I mean by that?
If we look, let's say, with nitrate first.
Well, on the right hand side of
the problem, I have two nitrates.
If I look on the other side of
the problem a little bit farther
away, we'll see that on the left
side, there's only one nitrate.
So if I go from 2 to 1, what's the
easiest way to balance that is by
putting a 2 out in front of nitrate.
Now like, this method is what I refer
to as a zigzag method, so being that
we have Two nitrates, we'll look at
hydrogen, so there's two on the left,
how many do I have on the right?
Well, being that we separated H and OH
for a reason here, to help us balance.
So in order to do that, we'll have two
hydrogens to balance the left and the
right, and we'll We'll then zigzag to
our OH, and we'll look, we have two
hydroxides on the right, and we also
have two on the right, on the left.
This is a balanced chemical reaction.
Alright, so now that we have
that, what is our next step?
So our next step in the problem is to list
out all the variables from the problem.
Now, why is that important?
Well, the reason behind this, it
helps us be organized and to see
what exactly are we being given.
So in this problem, the first thing
that we have is that we have 0.
45 molar of HNO3.
And then we were also given
what the concentration and
volume was of barium hydroxide.
So we have 0.
245 molar of barium hydroxide.
And it has a volume of 27.
2 milliliters.
So, why do we do this?
It's because it helps tell you
where to start the problem.
Our next step is to do stoichiometry.
When it comes down to doing solution
stoichiometry, we need to be
able to map out our pathway here.
When it comes to solutions, the idea is,
is that we need to start with a volume of
one ingredient and convert it to moles.
moles are always the goal.
So how do we do that?
Well, the only way to really be
able to bridge from volume to
moles is by using molarity, right?
Molarity is a conversion term
that is very useful to us.
So that is bridged by molarity of.
In this case, molarity of
A to get the moles of A.
So what that tells you is the only
place that you can start is with
a chemical that has That's a both.
of both the molarity and the volume.
You need both things to start.
Both molarity, volume and
molarity is where you start.
So when we do that, we can then convert it
to moles of B, which we can then convert
to volume of B using the other molarity.
So typically you're given one, maybe
potentially two concentrations here.
So we'll use the other molarity
to do that, which was our HNO3.
So the thing we're going to
start with is barium hydroxide.
So that is where we will start.
So why don't we copy our
information from up here.
Uh, so we'll have our chemical equation
with us and then our variables.
All right.
So let's bring that down.
So we have our problem here.
What we're going to do is we're
going to set up a stoichiometry
process for ourselves.
So we'll first have our volume is
what we said we would start with.
So we'll have 27.
2 milliliters.
Now our goal is to convert that to moles.
So what is molarity?
Let's take a look.
Molarity is moles.
Over liters.
So if I have my barium hydroxide,
that is saying that we have
0.245 moles over liters.
Now, is there another way that this can be
represented to make this a little easier?
Well, there is.
So if you think about being that this
problem has to be in milliliters,
how many milliliters are in a liter?
Well, you might remember 1000
milliliters is one liter.
So we can actually
represent this two ways.
We can just say 0.
245 moles is over 1, 000
milliliters or over 1 liter.
It's a shortcut.
So it's always good to have those
little shortcuts for ourselves.
So let's plug that in.
So if we have that 0.
245 moles of barium hydroxide, and
that's over 1, 000 milliliters, Now,
why is that important is the MLs
now cancel the MLs, they're gone,
and all we have is moles of barium
hydroxide, which was our first step.
Now, why did we have to balance
the chemical equation earlier?
Well, that was so that we can
know the mole to mole ratio.
So, our next step is that we'll have
one mole of barium hydroxide, And
that's equivalent to 2 moles of nitric
acid based on our chemical equation.
So that cancels moles of barium hydroxide.
That goes away.
Now we have to convert it to volume.
And we'll do the same trick with the
molarity of nitric acid, which is 0.
450 moles.
Over one liter or over 1000
milliliters being that our final
answer has to be in milliliters.
So let's plug that in.
So we need to set it up so units
cancel, they have to be opposites.
And this is going to
give us our final volume.
And if you have to put it in liters
for you, maybe for your homework that
you have for your class, then you can
you can put you can leave it in over
one liter if that helps you as well.
Bye bye.
You have either option, but you can
see all those units are canceling
out as we go through this process and
let's pick a different color here.
Just so You can help illustrate
the differences here of
all these things canceling.
All right.
Now, when we solve, what are we doing?
We're multiplying everything on
top, dividing what's on bottom.
So we have 27.
2 milliliters times 0.
245 moles times two
moles times a thousand.
We'll then divide that by a
thousand, divide that by 0.
450 and what we are going to get is 29.
62 milliliters.
of nitric acid is required
to neutralize this.
Now we want to make sure we put in the
right sig figs, so this is going to be 29.
6 mL is going to be our
final answer of nitric acid.
And that is how we do
this style of problem.
Let's go into the next one.
So if I had the following example,
which says calculate the pH of a strong
base solution If you use 5 grams of
calcium hydroxide to make a total of 2.
5 liters of solution, what is the pH?
How do we use a pH equation?
Well, one of the big things
about any of those is that it
comes down to identifying, is
this an acid or is this a base?
So the ingredient that we were given
in the very beginning was calcium
hydroxide, which if you remember, anything
that has a hydroxide in it is a base.
Thanks.
So this one is going to be, we
can only solve for POH first.
So let's write how this is going to
dissociate because we want to know how
much hydroxide there is in solution.
So if this breaks apart, we have
one calcium ion and two hydroxide
ions that are in solution, right?
So both of these are
in their aqueous state.
And they are dissolving well now why?
Why is that important?
Well, we were only given how many
grams of calcium hydroxide we have to
convert that to moles of hydroxide.
Why moles?
Well, remember our formula is POH
is equal to the negative log of the
concentration of oh minus, meaning
that oh minus has to be in molarity.
So we have to go from moles
and then divide it by the
liters that are in solution.
So we have to use, uh, a few
different pieces of information
that are here, right?
We have the 2.
5 liters and the 0.
5 grams that are here.
So let's first calculate moles.
Let's go from 0.
5 grams of calcium hydroxide
to moles of hydroxide.
So when we are doing that, we're
going to map out our reaction, right?
So we're going to go from grams to moles.
And that's for calcium hydroxide and then
we are going to go to moles again using,
uh, that one mole of calcium is equivalent
to two moles to two moles of hydroxide.
Okay.
So map out your process.
It makes it a little bit easier
when you're trying to figure out
exactly what is it that you are
trying to work on in your problem.
So, With that, we will
determine the concentration.
So we started with 0.
5 grams of calcium hydroxide.
We need to multiply
that by the molar mass.
So the molar mass, when you look up
and calculate those values, it's 73.
968 grams of calcium hydroxide
per mole of calcium hydroxide.
So when we do that, we'll
see the grams cancels grams.
And now the next step is we have to
do the mole to mole equation, which
as we saw earlier is that one mole
of calcium hydroxide dissociated
into two moles of hydroxide.
So now when we do that, we can see
that, all right, the moles cancel and it
gives us how much hydroxide is in there.
Now remember, this is
not what the molarity is.
This is only how many moles there are.
So, when we solve that, we'll have 0.
0135 moles of hydroxide.
Now how do you find a concentration?
Well, this is where we have to treat
molarity like a formula, right?
Molarity is moles over liters.
So we're going to plug in
our moles and our liters.
So we'll put moles on top.
And then we'll divide it by how
many liters of solution are,
which were 2.5 liters of solution.
Now, when we do that, we will get our
final molarity, which is 5.4 times 10 to
the negative three molar of hydroxide.
Okay?
So that's the oh minus concentration, and
that's our important value there, right?
So that's what that is telling us.
Now, how.
Let's actually go and solve
what our equation was.
So we just had to set it up there.
The first thing with pOH, right,
is that we take the pOH of
the negative log of OH minus.
So we are going to plug in
our number into this equation.
So we'll have the negative log of 5.
4 Times 10 to the negative three molar.
And what that's going to give us
is a POH of 2.27 as our value.
Now, are we finished?
Well, let's check the original problem.
So if we scroll up here for a second
and we go, it says, what is the pH?
So what's our last step?
Well, if you remember,
there's a bridge between pH.
And P O H.
So, with this, is that P H and P O H, when
you add them together, is equal to 14.
So, what we have to do is subtract the
P O H from the P, from the 14 value.
So, 14 minus 2.
27 is going to equal the P H, meaning
that that is being plugged in here.
So when we do that, it's going
to tell us that our pH is 11.
73, which when we see that,
that is extremely basic from
our values that we have.
Thank you so much for watching this video.
I hope that this helped with
your general chemistry needs.
If you need anything else for different
practice problems, feel free to like
and comment down below so that way
I can help you with future content.
Please subscribe for more videos,
more practice problems, and how
to tutorials are to come to help
you pass your chemistry class.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.